Finding Aid for Herman Lunden Papers 1896-1929
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Herman Lunden Papers 1896-1929
Lunden, Herman, 1859-1929.
5.5 linear feet
Timber manager of the Kneeland Bigelow Company of Bay City, Michigan. Autobiography; correspondence, 1899-1924 (scattered); Kneeland-Bigelow Company records, 1912 and 1923-1929; subject files relating to his interest in conservation, reforestation, forest fire prevention, local Republican party affairs, road improvement, and the development of the northern Lower Peninsula as a tourist and recreational region.
85276 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Herman Lunden Miller (donor no. 6938 ) and has come to the library in several accessions.
The collection is open for research.
Herman Lunden was born in Sweden in 1859, the son of a lumberman. In 1877 as a young man still in his teens, he immigrated to the United States to seek work in the lumbering camps and sawmills of Michigan.
During the 1890s Lunden was company scout for Michelson and Hanson Lumber Company. Because the company would not exploit hardwoods and thus lengthen the life of the operation, Lunden decided to strike out on his own. Needing capital for his venture, he approached David Kneeland, the supervisor of Michelson and Hanson's general office in Lewiston, Michigan. In turn, Kneeland went to Charles Bigelow, a successful Bay City lumber salesman. The two men decided to provide the necessary capital and in 1901 the Kneeland-Bigelow Company was formed.
Lunden served as the coordinator for all of the company camps in Montmorency County. The first camp was about five miles north of Lewiston in Montmorency County. A permanent headquarters was later established at K-B Valley, nine miles west of Atlanta, Michigan. All K-B timber was shipped by the Michigan Central Railroad to Bay City where the main office and two sawmills were located. During the next few years Lunden gradually shifted his base of operations into Otsego and Cheboygan counties.
Eventually Kneeland-Bigelow had camps spread throughout Montmorency, Otsego, Presque Isle, Cheboygan and Crawford counties. The company owned approximately 27,500 acres of land, carrying about 700,00,00 feet board measure, and the timber rights on about 15,000 additional acres.
Herman Lunden, in addition to his business interest, was active in various public service endeavors. He served on the State Conservation Commission during the early 1920s where he championed the cause of reforestation and fire prevention. Lunden was also involved in various county road commissions and the Michigan Association of Road Commissions and Engineers, where he argued that "good roads" were essential to the development of the business and recreational potential of the upper and northern lower peninsula. A booster to his home region, Lunden served on the Upper Peninsula Development Bureau and the Tri-State Development Congress, and was a supporter of the Northeastern Michigan Development Bureau. Lunden was an active Republican, serving on the Republican State Central Committee.
Herman Lunden died January 11, 1929 after having given a talk before the Bay City Chamber of Commerce about the paving of M-76 from Standish to Roscommon.
Documenting his business and public service activities, the Herman Lunden papers cover the period from the late 1890s to 1929. The collection includes Biographical/Personal material; Correspondence; Kneeland-Bigelow records; and an Alphabetical File.
Subjects:
Bay City (Mich.)--Businesses.; Business records.; Conservation of natural resources--Michigan.; Kneeland-Bigelow Company.; Logging--Michigan.; Lumbering--Michigan.; Lunden, Herman, 1859-1929.; Montmorency County (Mich.); Republican Party (Mich.); Roads--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Camping.; Cheboygan (Mich.); Dogsleds.; Exhibitions.; Gaylord (Mich.); Industrial buildings--Michigan--Lewiston.; Kneeland-Bigelow Company.; Laborers.; Lewiston (Mich.)--Industrial buildings.; Lumber industry--Michigan.; Lunden family.; Michaelson and Hanson Lumber Company.; Michigan State Normal College--Students.; Railroads--Michigan.; Roads--Michigan.; Woodcutting.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical/Personal
  The collection begins with a series of Biographical/Personal material that includes autobiographical information and photographs. The photographs include a ca. 1925 traveling railroad exhibit on reforestation and forest fire prevention; copy prints of the Dixie motorcade pilot car and passengers, ca. 1925, an event intended to gather support for improved roads for motor vehicles; photos of Michelson and Hanson Lumber Company sawmill at Lewiston, Mich.; and photographic postcards, ca. 1900-ca. 1910, of lumbering scenes, dogsled at Cheboygan, Mich., and family
  - Autobiography; obituaries; company history; clippings, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Information on the Lunden papers (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 5 folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series is a combination of personal and Kneeland-Bigelow papers. These papers were originally stored in letter boxes and arranged alphabetically. Some of these materials (those received first) were arranged chronologically. Those letter boxes received subsequently were maintained as an alphabetical file. The correspondence related mainly to business matters although there is much that concerns Lunden's other civic and political interests.
  - 1896-1899 (arranged alphabetically), 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1899-1904, 9 folders (Box 1)
  - 1911-November 1912, 11 folders (Box 1)
  - 1911-1912 (arranged alphabetically), 4 folders (Box 1)
  - 1912-1913 (arranged alphabetically), 4 folders (Box 2)
  - 1923-June 1926, 29 folders (Box 2)
  - July 1926-August 1929, 53 folders (Box 3)
- Kneeland-Bigelow
  The Kneeland-Bigelow series includes correspondence filed by name of correspondent and a variety of financial information, including financial statements and monthly financial reports. From both the Correspondence and Kneeland-Bigelow series, the researcher will gain a fairly good sense of how an early 20th century lumber company operated. The files document the problems associated with the production and sale of lumber, the company's relationship with its work force, and other larger issues, such as what Lunden and the Kneeland-Bigelow Company thought about issues of conservation and reforestation.
  - Correspondence (by name)
    - Baker, R.G. (Box 4)
    - Bigelow, Charles A.
      - 1911 (Box 4)
      - 1912-1913 (Box 4)
      - January-July 1925, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - McVey, A.W. (K-B traffic manager) (Box 4)
    - Wrape, Walter N. (K-B secretary-treasurer) (Box 4)
  - Financial
    - Annual financial statements 1923, 1926, 1928, 5 folders (Box 4)
    - Monthly financial reports 1902-1913, 1924-1928, 1931-1937, 6 folders (Box 4)
    - Liquidation materials 1945-1965 (Box 4)
    - Stockholder list (Box 4)
  - Timber estimates 1920, 1928 (Box 4)
  - Pocket notebooks; include estimator's plat books 1903-1928 (scattered dates), and memorandum and appointment books (Box 4)
- Alphabetical files (people and organizations)
  The last series in the collection - Alphabetical Files - consists of subject and name files pertaining to Lunden's other interests in conservation (particularly reforestation and forest fire prevention), in the economic development of the upper lower peninsula, and with that, in the need for good roads and highway development in that region (he was for a time chairman of the county road commission and was forever writing letters about the need to improve the roads in that area of the state), and also in Republican party activities in Montmorency county. The researcher should note that Lunden's correspondence files also contain information about his other activities apart from Kneeland-Bigelow.
  - Alpena News 1927-1928 (Box 4)
  - Atlanta and Lewiston banks 1926-1928 (Box 4)
  - AuSable Club 1927-1928 (Box 4)
  - Bigelow, Charles A. (personal correspondence) 1928, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Bloomer, Howard B. 1926-1927 (Box 4)
  - Buttles, Bruce 1926-1929 (Box 4)
  - Chambers of commerce 1927, 1929 (Box 4)
  - Church activities 1927-1929 (Box 4)
  - Comstock, C.W. 1927 (Box 4)
  - Conservation (miscellaneous) (Box 4)
  - Conservation, Department of
    - Correspondence 1924-1929, 8 folders (Box 4)
    - Financial statements 1924-1925 (Box 4)
    - Forest fire district reports 1926 (Box 4)
    - Minutes of meetings 1926 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Review of accomplishments 1921-1926 (Box 4)
  - Cottrell, Charles 1928 (Box 5)
  - County road commissions 1925-1929 (Box 5)
  - DeLaMater, G. F. 1928 (Box 5)
  - Detroit, Mackinac and Marquette Land Company 1928-1929, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Doelle, John A. 1928 (Box 5)
  - East Michigan Tourist Association 1927-1928, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Fair associations 1928 (Box 5)
  - First National Bank, Sault Ste. Marie 1926 (Box 5)
  - Forest Fire Fighting Flyer (with photographs) (Box 5)
  - Forest fire report summaries 1925 (Box 5)
  - Geological surveys, Afton, Cheboygan County 1927 (Box 5)
  - Green, Fred W. 1926-1928 (Box 5)
  - Henshaw, Fred W. 1928 (Box 5)
  - Itinerary 1921: "Around Lake Superior" International Good Roads Tour (Box 5)
  - Jenson, Lewis 1927 (Box 5)
  - Jerusalem artichokes 1926-1928 (Box 5)
  - Kiwanis Club 1927-1928 (Box 5)
  - Kneeland, Pierson (personal correspondence) 1927-1928, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Lewiston, Mich., sketch map circa 1900 (Box 5)
  - Lewiston and South Eastern Railroad 1896-1897 (Box 5)
  - Lincoln Press Co. 1928 (Box 5)
  - Lower Peninsula Land Owners 1927 (Box 5)
  - Lunden, Lester 1929, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - MacKenzie, J.S. 1928 (Box 5)
  - Michigan Agricultural College/Michigan State College Cooperative Extension Work 1923-1928 (Box 5)
  - Michigan Bankers Association 1928, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Michigan Children's Aid Society 1911-1928 (scattered) (Box 5)
  - Michigan Committee-Herbert Hoover for President 1928 (Box 5)
  - Michigan legislature 1912-1927 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Montmorency County (various county records) (Box 5)
  - Montmorency County Republican Party 1924-1928 (Box 5)
  - National Gypsum Company 1928 (Box 5)
  - New York Central Lines-Agriculture Relations Department 1926-1928 (Box 5)
  - Noble Oil and Gas Company 1926-1928 (Box 5)
  - Northeastern Michigan Development Bureau (correspondence and financial reports) 1926-1928, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Northern Michigan Road Commissioners Association
    - Constitution and bylaws (Box 5)
    - Correspondence 1924-1928, 10 folders (Box 5)
  - Northwestern Michigan Oil Development 1927-1929, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Rea, Ford C. 1927-1928 (Box 5)
  - Remington, Ellsworth 1928 (Box 5)
  - Republican National Committee 1927-1928 (Box 6)
  - Republican National News Service 1926 (Box 6)
  - Republican State Central Committee 1912, 1924-1928, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Republican (miscellaneous) (Box 6)
  - Road builders associations 1928 (Box 6)
  - Second National Bank of Saginaw 1925-1926 (Box 6)
  - Speeches (mostly concerning reforestation) (Box 6)
  - Stace, Arthur W. 1928 (Box 6)
  - State Highway Department 1925-1928, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Stoll, Albert 1926 (Box 6)
  - Tri-County Sportmen's Club 1928 (Box 6)
  - Tri-State Development Congress 1924 (Box 6)
  - U.S. Department of Agriculture 1925-1928 (Box 6)
  - U.S. Department of Agriculture-University Farm, St. Paul, Minnesota 1924-1928 (Box 6)
  - U.S. Forest Service 1928 (Box 6)
  - University of Michigan 1927-1929 (Box 6)
  - Upper Peninsula Development Bureau 1924-1928 (Box 6)
  - Wallace, W.H. 1927-1928 (Box 6)
  - Weber, Frank 1924-1926 (Box 6)
  - Welsh, George 1926 (Box 6)
  - Welsh for Governor Committee 1928 (Box 6)